and what I'm doing is that I I I just
clean it when very carefully with this
cloth and then when i get the the worst
of the wetness out that I start a new
procedure to dry out to help it to draw
out quickly and not drawing like this I
the reason is because if you could see
this in the electromagnetic scope then
you will see huge black mountains
turning from black and then when you
blow the bomb it looks like dark copper
so you don't want you don't want to
destroy the upper layer all those small
moments and then when this plate is
driving which is the case now you take a
new container
and just a small amount of estimated
water
the reason is because desolated water is
smoother than salt water and the reason
for this procedure is because you don't
want the amount of caustic soda to
interfere too much with the operation
from the number of field get thing its
secret marriage with the with a metal
when you can see not boiling reactions
it's getting clearer and make sure that
the whole surface as a full amount of
the selected water it has to dry because
you don't want to take the water
molecules from the disconnected water
into the saltwater
this is a practical a little thing too
long
that's when you attach the Copperfield
you press it like this
why because then you are sure that the
connections are connection then i
connect the the plate