alright so in this video we're going to
be building a complete tasks list
application using the mean stack now if
you don't know what the mean stack is it
stands for MongoDB Express angular and
nodejs
now there are packages and modules or
frameworks that were created to really
streamline a lot of this process and
basically set you up with a boilerplate
for a mean application alright I do know
that no those exist
feel free to still tell me about them in
the comments but I'm not using one of
those because you're not going to learn
too much from that all right if you
really want to be a good developer and
actually know what you're doing and
understand it it's better to basically
do it from scratch alright so learn it
understand what's going on and then move
on to those those tools that can
basically do all this stuff for you all
right so before we begin I just want to
mention that this is from a prime
angular 2 project based course it's not
from it but it is it's based off it so
if you do like this I would suggest
checking that out and I'll leave the
link in the description all right so I
have 4 tabs open here and I just want to
kind of go through what we'll be working
with
so for MongoDB we're going to use a
service called M lab which will give us
a remote implementation of MongoDB so we
don't have to worry about installing it
on your machine and getting that set up
it it does have some really expensive
plans but it does have a free sandbox
plan which is what we'll use all right
so we'll get that set up now the e in
mean stands for Express and Express is a
framework that you can install in you
can use to build web applications
it features routing API is to work with
HTTP requests and just a whole bunch of
different stuff for building
applications and running a server
alright so we'll get that set up
obviously angular is going to be used
for the front end for the the the client
side you I will build a task list
component and we'll also build a service
that will interact with our Express
server
all right now we're going to be using
something called Mongo Jas which is an
ORM that allow us to interact with our
MongoDB database and do inserts and
finds and stuff like that all right and
then of course we need nodejs
if you don't have that installed just go
to node.js org and download and install
that alright and that obviously that
comes with NPM as well okay I mean
hopefully you guys know at least a
little bit you know what NPM is and
stuff like that if you don't I would
suggest maybe going back into some of
them maybe the Express crash course
things things like that some of the more
beginner based courses alright so let's
go ahead and get started first thing
we're going to do is create a project
folder so I'm gonna go let's see where
am I going to go in my C Drive let's see
we'll go into sandbox and obviously you
can create your application wherever you
want I'm going to create a folder and
we're just going to call this we'll call
it my task list all right as far as the
functionality it's going to be very
basic the idea is just to get you
familiar with the technologies and how
they all go together all right so let's
open up a command line in that folder
I'm just going to use my standard
Windows command prompt and feel free to
use whatever you'd like for this and
let's say I want to make this font a
little bigger
alright yeah that should be good I'm
sure you guys can see that all right so
let's go into the folder I just created
all right and first thing we're going to
do is pretty much set up node and then
set up Express all right so we need to
have a package.json file which is
basically a manifest it has the
application name the version all that
stuff and it also will contain all the
dependencies that we need all right so
to create that we can say npm in it and
that should start to ask us some
questions here it's going to ask us the
name my task list is fine so we're going
to click enter version that's good
description will just say simple task
manager entry point I'm going to call it
server J s and then just enter through
the rest all right and that should have
created a package.json file alright now
i'm going to open up my editor and i'm
using visual studio code which is really
nice it's free if you want to check that
out or you can use whatever you like
alright so I'm going to open up that
folder and let's take a look at the
package.json file basically just has all
the stuff that we just answered alright
so now what we want to do is install all
of our dependencies ok so we can do that
through our command line so say npm
install and we want express we want body
parser we want to be able to accept data
except data through a form and parse
that and then submit it to the database
we're also going to use ejs as our
template system and Mongo j/s ok Mongo J
s will allow us to interact with MongoDB
and that should be it so let's do - -
save and that'll add it to add these to
our package JSON file
all right so now if we look at package
Jason you can see that we have our
dependencies all right so now we're
going to create the server J s file okay
this will be our main back-end server
file so we're going to first bring in
what we need to so we'll create a
variable called Express and we'll set
that to require Express all right that's
just going to bring Express in from the
node modules folder which is right here
all right we also want to bring in our
path module now path is a system module
that's why we didn't have to install it
separately and that'll just help us work
with file system paths and stuff like
that hence the name path okay we also
want to bring in the body parser all
right and now we're going to do we're
going to have two files in a folder
called route and one will be for index
which will basically just be our index
page our home page and then will be one
will be tasks which will be the API that
that we want to create so we can work
with MongoDB so we're going to create a
variable called index and set that to
require and it's going to come from
routes oops
routes slash index all right and then
I'm going to just copy that and then
this one here will be tasks
alright now let's create our main app
variable we're going to set that to
Express alright then we'll set up the
view engine okay first of all we'll let
the system know what folder we want to
use for our views so say app dot set and
we're going to set views then we need
the path we're going to use the path
module here say path dot join and then
I'm going to pass in a double underscore
do our name and then views okay so
that's going to tell the system our
views will be in the views folder now we
need to specify the engine
so we'll say app dot set view engine and
we're going to tell it that we want to
use ejs all right now we also want to be
able to render files with an HTML
extension so we're going to say app dot
engine oops app dot engine and then
we'll pass in HTML and then we're just
going to require ejs and we just want to
do dot render file alright so that sets
up the view engine now we're going to
need a static folder and that's where
we're going to put all the angular stuff
alright so we'll say set static folder
and for that we need to do app dot use
and say Express dot static and then
we're going to use the path join here
again say do our name and specify the
name of the folder we want and that'll
be client okay so all the angular two
stuff will go in the client folder next
thing we'll do is the body parser
middleware
so say app dot use this is just standard
middleware if you look at the body parts
or documentation this is right from that
we want to be able to parse Jason
alright we also want body parser dot URL
encoded and we're going to pass in here
an object and say extended bolts okay so
that's the body parts or middleware now
we're going to do is create our route so
app dot use and we want the slash which
is just basically the homepage we want
that to be associated with the index
route okay so are the index route file
which is up here alright and then for
the tasks the URL will be slash API okay
and then we'll put in here tasks okay so
whenever we want to interact with the
API will use that slash API now we want
to do is just basically listen so we can
run our server so app dot listen we want
to put in the port we want which I'm
actually going to put a variable up here
and put the port in that so we'll set it
to 3,000 all right
actually no set it to all three 3,000 is
good all right and then port will pass
that in and then this also takes a
callback function so we can do something
after it connects and all I want to do
is just do a console log and we'll just
say server started on ports and then
we'll just concatenate that port
variable alright so that should do it
for our server let's save it
and if we go ahead and run a node server
oops what's this cannot find module
routes index oh we have we need to
create the routes folder and these files
I didn't even think of that so let's
create a folder and we're going to call
that route and it's going to have a file
called index dot JSON
okay let's start with the index and this
file is going to be pretty short we're
going to just bring in Express and then
we want to use the Express router so
we're going to save our router equals
Express dot rotor alright and then we
want to set our route for the home page
so router dot get because it's going to
it's going to accept a get request and
it's going to be just slash alright and
then that'll take a function and these
Ralph callback functions will take a
request response and next and all we're
going to do right now is say res dot
send and we'll just say index index page
okay then we just need to export this so
that we can access it from other files
and we want to explore it the router
alright and I'm just going to copy
everything here save it and then we'll
add that to tasks as well and then for
right now just going to change this to
tasks or tasks API and just change this
right here to tasks alright so we'll
save that now we're going to get an
error still because we don't we don't
it's going
to look for the views folder and we'd
haven't created that yet so let's go
ahead and create that
and inside views we're just going to
create a file called index.html all
right and I'll get to that in a second I
just want to make sure that this will
run so node server you can see it says
service started on port 3000 and if I go
to localhost 3000 we get our index page
if I go to slash API slash tasks we get
that tasks API alright all we're doing
right now is this root res dot sin which
just sends this whatever we put in here
to the browser all right now ultimately
with the index we want to display our
route our template so what I'm going to
do is change this to res dot render and
then just pass in here index dot HTML
alright and then inside index.html we'll
just create some HTML tags and actually
let's put a doctype alright and then in
our HTML tags we'll put a head and put a
title
body all right so let's save that and we
need we're going to need to restart the
server because right now if I go we're
still going to get that index page so
let's ctrl C and then restart it and now
if we reload we get our index.html file
now this can be kind of a pain to have
to keep reloading the server like this
so I would suggest using something
called node Mon and you can install that
globally so that you can run it from
anywhere so to do that we can say NPM
install - G make sure you use that to
make it global and then node Mon and
that will just monitor your your server
and update whenever you make any changes
all right so now instead of node server
we're going to just run node Mon alright
you'll see it's it's watching so now if
I were to let's say add an exclamation
mark and save it without reloading the
server you can see that it actually does
update all right so now that we have our
Express server up and running what we
want to do is start to use Mongo j/s to
interact with our database now we I
haven't created the database yet so I'm
going to go to my M lab and just log in
alright go ahead and create an account
if you don't have one and then we're
going to say create new and we're going
to leave the Amazon Web Services as the
default cloud provider and then if we
click on single node and then check the
sandbox account that's the free account
and then for the database name
I think it has to be unique I'm just
going to say my task list Brad you can
call it whatever you'd like okay so that
should turn to a check there we go so
that means it's setup now if we click on
that you should see a page like this and
what you want to do first is add a user
okay so if we go to users and we click
Add database user just going to put my
name and for all for the username and
password and then create okay so now you
can see we have a user and then if we go
to collections I'm going to click add
collection and we're going to create a
collection called tasks all right and if
we click on tasks we can now add a
document we can add data from here so
let's go ahead and add a simple task
it'll have a title
hope you guys can see that okay so we'll
say walk the dog okay so it's going to
just have a title and it's also going to
have is is done okay we're going to hit
call it is done and that's going to be
set to false all right so if we go
create and go back let's see why am I
getting an error
all right forgot the comma all right so
now you'll see that we have the title we
have the is done and it also gives us
this underscore ID which is equal to a
unique object ID so we don't have to
worry about that all right now let's
create a couple more okay title and
we'll just say go food shopping
is done false okay so that got added
let's add one more title oops
say go out to dinner is done is false
alright so now we have a couple tasks to
work with so let's go back to our
application and now we're going to go
into route tasks j/s this is the main
API that we'll be creating
so we want to bring in Mongo J s so say
var Mongo J s and require ok then we
want to create a database object we're
going to set that to Mongo J s and then
here's where we want to pass in our
database information so if we go back to
M lab and go to back to our database
landing page here and you can see we
have a way to connect to the de Mongo
shell and a way to connect using a
driver so we want this one with the
driver and yours will be different so
just grab that paste that in there and
then we need to replace the DB user here
with your the date the username you
created as well as the password alright
and then at the end here we're going to
add another parameter and this is an
array of the collections you want to use
okay and the only collection we have
that we want to use is tasks all right
and now we should be able to work with
this DB variable so instead of this res
dot sin let's get that out of there and
we'll say DB dot tasks
dot find all right now inside find we're
going to put a function and that will
take an error and Docs or actually let's
call it tasks it's more descriptive and
we'll check for an error so if there is
in fact an error we're just going to do
res dot send sorry about that and then
we'll send the error if there's not then
we're just going to we're going to
return the JSON content so I'm going to
say res day tsin and then just pass in
the tasks all right so let's save that
and hopefully this works let's go ahead
and go to slash API slash
tasks and there they are so we're
returning the JSON content for those
tasks that we created alright so that
takes care of that now we also want to
be able to get a single task all right
let me just add a comment here this will
get all tasks we also want to get single
tasks why is it doing it all right so
what I'm going to do is just copy this
whole thing and we're going to say
router get this time I'm going to say
task slash colon ID which is basically a
parameter or just kind of a placeholder
because the ID is going to be dynamic
it's going to be different every time
all right and then we're going to say DB
tasks and then we can use this find one
and then before the function we'll have
an opera meter and that's going to be
basically the condition so we want to
say where underscore ID is equal to the
ID that's passed now since it's an
object ID that's stored in the database
we have to run it through this Mongo
Mongo j/s dot
object ID and then pass in the ID that's
passed in the URL and to get that we
need to use request dot params ID all
right and then we're just going to
change this tasks to singular tasks and
change it right here as well all right
and that should get us a single task so
let's save it and then what we'll do is
grab let's say that go out to dinner ID
and in the URL will say API slash
task slash and then paste in that ID and
you can see it's going to return just
that one task all right so so far so
good now we want to be able to save
tasks as well all right so for that
we're going to need to do a post request
or handle a post request okay so what
we'll do is we'll say router dot post
okay instead of get and the URL will be
slash tasks all right then do a function
going to take the same thing request to
response next and we're going to get the
the task from a form so we'll create a
variable called task and we'll set that
to request dot body ok that's how we can
get it from the form and then we're
going to do just a very simple
validation we'll say if not task dot
title or task dot is done and then we're
just going to concatenate just a blank
string there all right and then we're
going to just send a 400 status so it's
going to be an error so res dot status
400 all right and then we'll also just
send some JSON which will be an object
and it will just have an error and we'll
just say bad data all right so that's if
there's an error and then we're going to
do an else right here and then that
means that everything went ok with the
form so now we can proceed to do DB
tasks dot save all right and inside here
we'll pass in the tasks and then our
function okay that function will take in
an error and task and we'll check for
the error we'll do the same thing we did
up here just grab that and paste that in
all right now we could test this using
some kind of program that will let us
make HTTP requests so curl or something
like that but I'm just going to hold off
for now and we'll test it when we get to
the angular application all right so
that's to save a task now to delete a
task let's do that and I'm just going to
copy I'm going to copy this because it's
kind of similar alright so delete task
let's paste that in this is going to be
router dot delete now it's going to have
this same you I'll now even though we
have task ID here we can still have it
here because it's a different type of
request it's a delete request that's a
get request all right and then we're
going to have DB tasks dot remove and
same thing we're going to pass in the ID
and the rest should be the same I
believe yeah that's fine all right so
that's a delete delete task
and finally we'll do the update all
right so for this let's grab I'll just
copy this alright so this here is going
to be a put request
so put pertains to when you're updating
data that's already on the server and
then what we'll do down here is get the
information from the form so our task is
going to be equal to request dot body
we're also going to create a variable
called UPD task which will represent the
updated task which I'll set to just an
empty object for now and then we're just
going to do some I guess validation I'm
going to say if task dot is done then
we're going to set that update task dot
is done set that to task dot is done all
right and then same with the title copy
that
so task dot title and then down here
we'll set this title to task title all
right and then let's check for the
actual object so I'm going to say if not
updated task then we're going to send a
response a status of 400 and then we'll
just send that res dot Jason and we'll
send an error and we'll just say bad
data all right so let's put an else here
okay this is where we'll do our query
I'm just going to copy what we have
right here our cut what we have there
and paste it inside the else all right
now I'm going to change remove to update
okay so updates going to take in the
condition which we're going to match the
ID and then after that we're going to
put a parameter we're going to put our
updated task object and then another one
which will just be an empty and empty
object and then of course our function
alright and then all this down here can
stay the same check for the error and
then just spit out the task in JSON
format so let's save that alright so
again we're not going to test this the
delete and the update right now we'll do
that when we get to angular all right so
everything should still work we
shouldn't get any errors or anything
like that good so I think our back end
is complete we now have an HTTP now have
a restful api so now it's time to work
on the front end on the angular part of
the application so we need to create our
client folder okay so let's go ahead and
do that and we're going to basically
just follow along with the with the
documentation if we go to angular do and
then get started and we scroll down to
this area here there's four main config
files we need to create okay so first we
have package JSON so we're going to just
copy that code and inside client let's
create a file called package dot jason
and we're just going to paste that in
change the name here to my task list and
that's all we're going to do the rest is
just all with its angular and all of its
dependencies
alright so let's save that next one is
TS config JSON which is the typescript
config file let's create that
client okay paste that in basically
telling the system we want to compile to
es5 and we want to use the common je s
modules okay this one is typing Jason
this is just the Taipings that angular
needs gates that save it and then system
J s config we're going to copy that
and then I'm going to create system j s
config and then just paste that in
alright so you can close those up and
now what we need to do is we need to run
npm install but from the client folder
alright so i'm actually going to open up
another command line alright and we're
going to navigate to that folder okay
and then we want to go to client and
then run npm install
alright so now we want to do is create
inside the client create our app folder
and now we're just building an angular 2
app okay there's a really no difference
whether we're using whether it's a mean
app or not
okay so let's create inside app if we go
to the documentation here we need to
create a file called app dot module dot
TS ok so inside the app folder we're
going to create that file app dot module
dot TS and we'll just grab what's here
alright and basically we're just
implementing ng module which basically
helps organize our code alright this
file here whenever we create a component
we have to import it in here and then
add it to ng module ok so the next file
we want is app component TS so let's
create that every every angular 2
application has a core app component so
let's grab that code and this is just
standard component code we import the
component package and then we add this
component decorator with a selector in
this case is my app and then a template
which in this case is just a string with
an h1 and then a class
alright so save that and then we have to
import that into app module ts ok so
we'll say import app component from
app dot component okay now we have to
add this we have to actually create two
new arrays here we're going to have
declarations and also bootstrap alright
and you can see that if we go down here
okay declarations in bootstrap we have
to add app component to both of these
okay and then the next one we want to
create is main TS so let's create that
main TS paste that in and this is
basically just bootstrapping our our
core app component so save that now
remember we're using typescript with
angular 2 so these need to be compiled
into into regular JavaScript in order to
run the application so what we'll do is
inside the command line where we're in
the client folder I'm just going to run
NPM start and that should compile all of
our TS you can see now there's a bunch
of JavaScript files alright and then if
we go to localhost 3,000 we get oh we
shouldn't have that oh we didn't we
didn't add the HTML code alright so
let's go back to our documentation here
and there's an HTML file here that we
need to grab this is what loads
everything and then we'll go into our
HTML file which is in the views folder
and replace that let's change the title
okay and everything else should be good
you can see that the custom tag here my
app that actually goes along with the
selector of app component es which is
right here my app alright so let's make
sure we save index.html and let's go and
reload and there we go so the angular
app is now running so if we open up the
console now I'm getting an error because
there is no style.css file and you can
see it's looking for one here it's
included so let's just create that will
create that inside the client folder so
new file Styles dot CSS and then that
error should go away alright and gonna
go ahead and just close everything else
out here so we want to use bootstrap for
our UI and there's a few ways we could
set that up I'm going to use Bower which
is a front-end package manager much like
NPM is for node and for the the backend
for the server so let's go ahead and go
into our command line the one that's in
the app root not in the client and I'm
going to stop that and if you don't have
Bower installed you just want to run NPM
install - G Bower I already have it
installed so I'm not going to run it but
you run that it'll get installed
globally and then you can use it to
install packages now when we use Bower
and we install a package like bootstrap
I want it to go in a folder called Bower
components inside the client folder so
to make it do that inside the root we're
going to create a new file and we're
going to call it dot Bower RC all right
and then we just need to put in an
object here and we're going to say
directory and we want the directory to
be - client slash bower components oops
alright actually we don't need that
first slash so let's go ahead and save
that and then we'll go back and we'll
say bower install bootstrap and we'll
add dash - save alright it'll also
install jQuery because jQuery is
actually a dependency for the bootstrap
JavaScript and now you'll see in client
we now have Bower components folder with
bootstrap and jQuery so now we have to
include it in the HTML so views
index.html and we'll go right up here
put in our link tag okay and then the
path is going to be bower components
slash bootstrap slash dist slash CSS
slash bootstrap dot CSS all right let's
save that and then I'm going to run
let's run node server
are you load and now you can see the
fonts change so bootstrap is now being
read so we're going to work on the the
UI alright and in our angular
application we're going to have a
component called tasks so in the app
folder we're going to create a folder
called components I spell that right
components yeah
and inside there we're going to have a
another folder called tasks now in this
application we're only going to have the
one task component but it's good to have
it in a separate folder just so just in
case you want to add more later on
so inside tasks let's create a file
called tasks component dot TS and also a
file called tasks component dot HTML
that'll be that'll be the template all
right so let's go to the TS file and
we're actually going to copy what we
have an app component TS okay then we'll
paste it in there and then we'll change
the selector to tasks and change
template to template URL and then change
that to app sorry not app tasks dot
component dot HTML alright then we'll
change the class two tasks component so
save that inside task component HTML for
now we're just going to put in the word
tasks alright now in order to use this
we have to import it into app module TS
so let's go ahead and do that
god I'm having a hard time spelling
component today so import tasks and
pulling it from components / tasks tasks
dot component and then we're going to
add it to the declarations and save it
alright and we should be able to use it
so let's go into our app component es
file and we'll go ahead and replace this
with tasks save that let's see
404 not found oh you know what we can do
here is inside the task component es at
the top here we're going to add module
ID and then module dot ID and save
alright so now it works in order to use
the relative path like this you have to
add that at the top here are just
somewhere within the decorator okay so
you can see our task component is now
showing now for the app component es I
want to also use a separate file for the
template so we'll say template URL and
we'll grab that change it to app dot
component dot HTML and also add the
module ID save that and then let's
create that file
and paste in tasks and we should get the
same thing alright and let's actually
put this in a container say container
alright and then let's put an h1 right
here and we'll just say my task list and
then we'll put an HR tag alright so now
we want to do is go to our task
component HTML and start to build that
UI ok so first thing we're going to have
is a form and let's see in this form
let's give it a class of well and then
we'll put it div with the class of form
group these are just bootstrap classes
all right and then we'll put an input
give it a type of text and a class of
form control and let's give it a
placeholder and we'll just say add tasks
all right and then below that we'll have
a div with the class of task list all
right now this is going to have three
columns it'll have a checkbox then the
task title and then the the delete
button alright so for now we're just
going to put some static stuff in here
and then we'll go on to create the
service and all that all right so let's
create a class here our div with the
class of call MD one this will be the
the column for the checkbox because we
want to be able to check them off and
make them and mock off is done so in
here would say input type equals
checkbox okay then we'll have a class
called call call MD let's do seven and
then this will be the title so for now
just say some tasks okay and then we're
going to have call MD five for
okay this will have a delete button
let's make it an input we'll give it a
type button a value of delete and a
class of BTN BTN danger alright so let's
take a look at that and it looks pretty
good okay so now that we have the the
basic UI we need to create our service
to interact with our API that we created
alright when you're using angular
services used to do stuff like like
communicate with an API because you want
that available across all your
components if we had multiple components
we don't want to write the same code in
each one we want to create a service
that will send it across them all
alright so in the app folder we're going
to create another folder called services
and now let's create a file and we'll
call this task dot service dot TS and
we're going to import a couple things
here ok so we want a package called
injectable because we want to be able to
inject this service as a dependency ok
and that's going to be from angular
slash core we're also going to use the
HTTP module to make requests to our API
so we want to include HTTP as well as
headers which will allow us to
manipulate the headers and those are
going to be from angular slash HTTP all
right we're also going to be using
observables we want to get our requests
and then send the data as an observable
so we want to use the map operator so
we're going to say import rxjs which is
reactive ik reactive extensions for
JavaScript slash add slash operator
slash map
all right and then to use the injectable
we need to add the decorator and then
we're going to create our class and it's
going to be called tasks service all
right and then let's create a
constructor and since we're using the
HTTP module we have to inject that into
the constructor so say private HTTP set
that to HTTP all right and then let's
just do a console dot log and we'll say
task service initialized and save it now
to be able to use this service we're
going to go into let's see we're going
to go into our app component TS and
we're going to import it so let's say
imports task service from services slash
task dot service and then we have to add
that as a provider so we're going to go
down here and say providers inside
brackets will just add tasks service
alright so we'll save that now since
we're using the HTTP module we have to
actually bring that into app module TS
so this is kind of a like a meeting file
for all the different components you
have in all the modules so import HTTP
module that's going to be from angular
slash HTTP and then we're going to add
that to the imports array right here
like that all right now if we reload the
application we're still not seeing that
the services initialize that's because
we have to inject it and we're going to
inject it into our task component
all right so we need to import that here
as well
okay so we're going to go dot dot slash
dot dot slash services task dot service
okay and then we're going to add a
constructor and we need to inject it
here so we'll say private tasks service
set of two tasks service all right so if
we save that reload now you can see that
it's been initialized okay so we can now
use it now we want to fetch the tasks
from our API so let's go back into the
service and we're going to create a
function here called get tasks and it's
going to be really simple we're going to
return and then we're going to use this
dot HTTP GET okay we want to make a get
request to our API which is at HTTP
localhost port 3000 slash API slash
tasks all right and we want to return it
as an observable and we're going to just
add the map the map operator here and
then say the response we want to change
to res dot jason okay we want to return
it as jason so we'll save that go back
into our task component and inside the
constructor we're going to say this dot
tasks service dot get tasks which is
what we just created and since this is
an observable we need to subscribe to it
alright and then in here we'll say tasks
and for now it's just console dot log
tasks all right let's see what that
gives us all right so now down here you
can see we're getting these objects and
if we look at them they're the tasks
from our API all right so we're
successfully getting them now what we
want to do is add them as a property in
our component so let's add up here we'll
say tasks and I'm going to set that to
the type of task which isn't created yet
that's why you see the red line now you
could just set this to whatever just an
array but I like to set I like to create
kind of a a model for our properties so
what we'll do is let's create a file not
in the app folder outside of the app
folder but it's still in the client
folder called task dot TS all right and
then all we're going to do is export a
class called
task which will have a title which will
be a string and also is done which will
be a boolean all right and then we're
just going to import that into our task
component
okay that'll be dot dot slash let's see
three times and then task alright so now
you can see that red lines gone now what
we want to do is instead of console
logging we're going to set this dot
tasks equal to that task that's coming
in from the observable and then we'll
have access to them inside of our HTML
file alright so we'll go back in there
and since this is an array of objects
we're going to use ng four to loop
through them so let's go right here and
we'll say div asterisk ng four and we'll
say let tasks or let tasks of tasks and
we'll put the ending div down here and
now we should have access to each tasks
so right here we'll put in our double
curly brace and say task dot title and
save alright so now we're pulling them
into our list so now that we're just
playing our tasks we want to be able to
add to them alright so we have our form
here so what we'll do is in the form tag
we want a submit event so we're going to
say submit equals and it's going to
equal attack a function called add task
and we're also going to pass along the
event object alright now for the title
here we're going to set this is going to
be its own property so we're going to
set an NG model and we're going to set
it to title and then we also need a name
attribute set to the same thing title
alright now if I save that I think we're
going to get an error if I reload okay
and we're getting an error because in
the latest version of angular 2 you need
to create you need to include
forms module if you're going to use ng
model so we need to go back to app
module TS and just go ahead and import
that okay that'll be from angular slash
forms and then we just need to include
it right here okay save that and now
that error is gone all right so we added
the ng model now let's go back to our
component and let's see we want to add
right here title and set that to string
and then let's go down and create our
add task which takes in an event and so
let's say event dot prevent default just
so it doesn't actually submit and let's
do a console log and we'll say this dot
title okay so now if we go back and
reload and I type in something and I
submit click enter you see we're getting
something so we know that we're
submitting the form we know that we can
grab the title now we want to do is
create a new object for our tasks that
we want to submit so we'll call this new
task set it to an object with a title of
this title which is whatever we type in
and then also is done which we want to
set to false initially alright and then
what we want to do is we need to have a
service function that's going to submit
it to the database okay I mean I could
you know I could do say this dot tasks
dot push
and then pass in the new task and you'll
see if I go and type something in and
submit it it's going to show up here but
if I reload it's gone because it's not
persisting to the database or to the API
so we have to do that so let's do this
dot task service dot add task and I know
we haven't created that yet but we will
and then pass in new task ok and it's
going to be an observable so we're going
to do dot subscribe and then in here
we'll do tasks and then we can do our
this dot task dot push and pass in that
new tasks are not the new task with the
task we get back and then we'll simply
clear the form by saying this dot title
equals nothing alright so we'll save
that let's go to our service and then
we're going to say add task and that's
going to take in that new task object ok
now we're using the HTTP module and we
need to set our headers so we're going
to say var headers equals new headers
and that should be an uppercase H right
here alright and then we'll say headers
dot pend and we're going to pass in here
content type ok content type we want to
be application slash Jason all right and
then we're going to return this dot HTTP
dot post
okay it's a post request and it's going
to go to HTTP localhost 3000 slash tasks
all right now the next parameter is
going to be that new task but we want to
send it as a string so we're going to
wrap it in json dot stringify all right
and then the next parameter will be an
object with the headers okay and we want
to map it so dot map res to res dot
jason and that should do it
save it okay so now let's just say my
new task and enter and we're getting an
error here
oh let's you go to slash API slash task
huh uncle ho's 3000 api / task let's see
what am I doing wrong here it might not
even be on this side yeah let's just
check out the EPI so if we go to routes
tasks okay we have router dot post going
to task hmm
so we're getting a 400 so if not task
title all right you know what let's see
what it is we're actually sending so in
our service let's do a console dot log
and I'm not going to cut this out just
so you guys can kind of follow along
alright so console log it alright so
we're getting title test is done fault
so that's correct that's what we want to
send
hmm
headers
oh there should be an exclamation mark
right here let's try that no it's still
not working
alright guys I'm going to pause the
video for a second and I'll be right
back
alright yes it just restarted the server
and it worked
so I don't know if you guys are having
that problem just try to restart the
server and this is correct
okay and make sure you have that
exclamation mark there alright so we're
going to move on now that we can add
tasks and I'll just add another one just
to prove it say pick up kids at school
okay so we can add it and I'm just going
to add a little CSS style just to I
don't like how these buttons are so
close actually not CSS let's just add in
the HTML we'll just put a line break
right there or two there we go
okay so we can read we can add to it now
we want to be able to delete these as
well so let's do that we have the delete
button right here so what we want to do
is add a click event so parentheses
click okay we're going to set this to
delete tasks and all we need is the ID
so we'll pass in task dot underscore ID
all right we'll save that and then let's
go into our component TS say delete task
it's going to take in an ID oops not a
TD and ID okay and then we're going to
create a variable called tasks and set
it to the current tasks all right and
then we're going to call a service
function so tasks service dot delete
task which we will create and then
that's going to take in the ID and it's
observable so I'm going to subscribe and
inside subscribe will say data alright
and then we're going to say if data dot
n is equal to 1 and what we want to do
is loop through we want to loop through
the task and then find the one that
matches that ID and then splice it out
of the array alright so we'll do a for
loop so 4 will say VAR i is equal to 0
and then as long as I is less than tasks
dot length okay we want a I plus plus 2
increment by 1 and then let's do an if
statement to check the IDs so we'll say
if
tasks I which is the current iteration
dot underscore ID is equal to the ID
that's passed in then we know that's the
one to delete so we'll say tasks dot
splice and pass in the iteration
variable and then one all right so let's
save that and then we need to create
that function on the service delete
tasks okay which takes in an ID and that
should actually be singular delete tasks
okay we're going to return this dot HTTP
this is going to be a delete request so
we're going to say delete and say HTTP
actually know what we're using this
localhost 3000 and we shouldn't have to
okay because we're on the same domain so
let's get rid of that we'll just say
slash API slash task slash and then we
just want to concatenate here the ID all
right and then we'll just map ok we'll
map that back res res dot Jason okay
let's try it out so test task let's say
we want to get rid of that goes away
reload and it stays gone alright so the
last thing I want to do here is I want
to be able to mark these off is done
right now if I check them and I reload
think that goes away all right so it's
useless so let's go ahead and do that
we're going to go to our HTML and go
inside aware the input for the check box
we're going to put some brackets and say
checked I'm going to say checked if task
dot is done
all right and then this is also going to
have a click event when it's clicked
it's going to call a function called
update status and then we're just going
to pass in the tasks all right so let's
save that go back to our component ts
file and we want to create this update
status function ok that's going to take
in the task and let's create a variable
will call this underscore task so we're
basically just creating a new object to
to update with so we'll set the I
underscore ID to task dot on the score
ID we'll set the title task dot title
and is done to exclamation task dot is
done all right and then after that we're
going to call a service function task
service dot update status pass in the
underscore task object and subscribe
okay and then here we'll say data and
we're going to set task dot is done
equal to exclamation task dot is done
alright and that should do it for us so
let's save it and then we need to create
that service function
okay passing tasks and I'm going to copy
what we have right here with our headers
and all this okay let's get rid of that
console.log paste that in so this is
going to stay the same and then we're
going to say HTTP dot put that's going
to go to API tasks and then the ID so
we're going to just concatenate on here
task dot underscore ID all right and
then this new task let's change that to
just task which is what's being passed
in up here and then the rest of the
stuff can stay the same all right so
let's save that hopefully this works so
let's say we went out to dinner let's
check that off reload and it stays
checked and you'll also notice if we go
to M lab and we look at tasks and go out
to dinner you'll see that is done is now
set to true all right
if I uncheck it reload
now you'll see it's not set defaults but
it's gone which is basically the same
thing if I were to set it again it'll go
back to true okay so that's it our task
list application is done I apologize if
this was too long or if any of it was
confusing I know there was a lot to it
but like I said if you know how to do it
from scratch you have a much better much
better handle on it than if you just use
some pre-made mean j/s or something like
that all right so that's it and again if
you guys liked this check out the course
that's in the description and please
subscribe leave a like whatever you can
do is fine and thanks for watching