hey guys my name is Victoria Henson and
I'm a test nerd I guess from Stockholm
Sweden and I would like to show you how
to write a quick API test using mocap
JavaScript testing framework and I want
to test the swappi the star wash open
API that's floating around and world
wide web um so at first what I want to
do here is I want to go into my dev
folder and I want to create a directory
for my project that I want to call Star
Wars on the scores x seating that while
I'm here I would like to initiate an NPM
product so it's very important that you
have known install prior to you know
taking on this tutorial so NPM in it
and I just want to click this pro
because I don't want to specify anything
this is a quick demo
ok great so we're in the side of the
phone we'll just take a quick look and
you can see there that we have a package
of Jason package a cat package of Jason
and you see here there's not much in
there so what we want to do now is that
we want to add some dependencies and
that first and foremost we would like to
add mocha
so NPM installed mocha and that just say
- Deb will automatically install mocha
and add it to the package JSON as a
dependency as a dev dependency we want
to cheat a little bit and use the same
thing when we add chai which is a
section library that supports mocha so
we want to add that also want to add
something called should and that's a BDD
kind of tool to make the scripts more
easy to read left but not least we would
like to add we quests so fire that up
and that takes a little while request is
a HTTP well it's it's module that allows
you to do HTTP requests directly from
terminal and and you know in scripts
Java scripts like this so it's pretty
cool um and we can just check here let's
cap the file again and sweet so we have
four new dependencies so what we want to
do now is that we want to create we want
to do a make dare we want to create a
test folder and we would like to see
into that test folder and from here uh
well I guess we can go back one step and
do do-do-do sublime oh let's crack open
sublime and we can see here that nice we
have a test folder we have some non
modules and we have the package adjacent
so what we want to do now is inside of
the test folder we want to create
something called test of Jas so that
would be our first test file basically
so what we want to do now is that we
want to define some variables so at
first I would like to add should and
that should be required should let's
close that and I'm a big copy paste or
on both good and bad terms of course ah
but let's add requests and let's change
this guy to requests we also like to add
a expect expect and as require we'd like
here we want to type shy um and we're
going to do eight dot expect we want to
call that expect so and also you need to
base your L that will take us to the
actual site that we're testing
and that is swappi Star Wars API all
right let's see that should be well that
should be enough
oh yeah we want to add util as well a
detail and you require require and you
so okay great so we want to add our
first test case here
now we're define the variables let's say
that we want to add the first test case
and oh yeah you can use Java code single
quotes preferably you want to use linter
for this but since this is just a quick
tutorial I just want it shut this room
real quick and let it be messy then edit
okay so we want to describe ah test case
or just check if you wish um
let's call it read we turn Luke return
loop we want to return Luke okay great
um and going to cheat a little bit here
so I just copy paste it in um something
that I prepared so basically what we do
here in this test case is that we are
using the request framework or yeah to
do a get request and we're using the
base URL over here and we're adding on
to that we're adding on people / one so
we're picking up the first person and
we're checking we have a instruction
here saying that we should get a 200
response and we also want to just
console.log the body just check it out
to see what else is in there okay great
so this little test here is finished so
we would like to go back here start with
X and we want to gun go in here and
Alice CD tests and try mocha try and see
what happens and here you can see that
we're getting back it responds with a
lot of things here and we have some
objects body objects here we have Luke
Skywalker we're as high as mass hair
color cetera et cetera let's see if we
can assert something else here in this
little gate the gaze of response so
let's go back to sublime text so inside
of here I would like to add a new
variable
um body object and that should you know
just be jsonparser just in case pause
the whole body and get that to me we
don't necessarily need that but just in
case let's use the expect certain
library try and expect body objects
let's let's get that guy let's gain get
name first let's get Luke and let's get
the name and then go outside of that to
equal Luke's guy Walker hope spanning is
correct that ah let's do one more thing
let's copy-paste this so that we can do
it a little quicker let's expect the
hair caller which was the second one I
believe to equal blonde um
and say this tuskys this test
and mocha fired it up and it passes so
we asserted that the name was Luke
Skywalker and O Hara call comes here
that hair color is blonde so that was
basically quick tutorial on how to
create a quick test with mocha or a
quick check with mocha and chai using
requests feel free to send me
suggestions on if there's any framework
you would like to Tory along I probably
be happy to to just take on that task
and jump straight into it if I feel that
the test framework is worth checking out
I have a couple of videos coming up so
stay tuned