well hello internet and welcome to my
sauce video tutorial in this tutorial to
show you all the cool things we can do
with sass as well as compass which is a
framework that is built on top of sass
and I have a whole lot to do so let's
get into it so you may ask yourself why
would we ever want to use sass well it's
basically going to allow us to write
more maintainable code faster now with
CSS you're normally going to be
targeting individual elements and then
styling those elements and the problem
with that is if you use the same
properties for multiple elements you're
going to have to type those properties
in over and over and over again
well sass is going to provide us with
variables and functions and a whole
bunch of other things that are going to
instead going to allow us to reuse those
properties that we're defining so for
example if we would just deal with color
what we would have here is let's say we
have e f de CD and this is very ugly
what sass is going to allow us to do
instead is to define a variable called
almond which represents this color and
then we would just type in this guy
right here and what that's going to
allow us to do is then anytime we want
to define our color we could instead
just type in almond which is very very
useful and this is how easy it is to
define variables inside of sass and
you're going to see much more of this as
the tutorial continues the thing that's
really cool is we're going to be able to
define a property once with a logical
name like you saw there with almond and
then reuse it over and over and over
again and what's also awesome about that
is we're going to be able to find that
logical name once and then use it
document wide and it's also going to be
very easy to change because it's going
to be located in one place another thing
that's great about sass is compass which
like I said before it's a framework
that's built on sass it's going to allow
us to automatically generate properties
create cross-browser CSS and a whole
bunch of other different things as
you'll see for example if you wanted to
define a y translation as well as a
scale on one of your objects or elements
in CSS you would have to type all of
this out instead with sass and compass
we could instead just go include and
then transform and then translate why
50% and scale by 1/2 throw that guy
side of their and compass is going to
automatically generate all this stuff
for you so that will work cross-browser
however you can see that this is much
more neat and tidy another thing that's
really cool about sass is we're going to
be able to use nesting rules for
different states so instead of typing
out this and dividing everything up
we're instead going to be able to come
in here and go horizontal nav and then
go for our link define our color for the
static link and then inside of here put
an and colon and hover and define our
color change whenever our link is
hovered over and we could throw almond
in there as well well since it's a
variable however we're going to type in
almond just like that so that's another
neat thing that we're going to be able
to use to organize our code and SAS is
also going to be able to automatically
for us compress all our code so our page
is load quicker it's also going to make
it easy to optimize for many different
screen sizes and in this tutorial I'm
going to focus in on the extension s CSS
version of SAS so when we jump over and
show you exactly how we're going to
install this now SAS is going to be used
with rails so that's the reason why it's
in my rails tutorial if you're wondering
why it's inside of there and that's
going to mean that you're going to need
to have rails automatically installed
inside of here for all this stuff to
work and in the description on the link
to my tutorial and exactly how to
install rails it's very very easy as a
website to basically walk you through
the whole entire process now after you
have all that setup let's make sure that
we have the proper versions of rails and
Ruby installed on our system and this is
what you're going to type into your
computer and your terminal it doesn't
matter if you are on Windows or if you
are on OSX or Linux or whatever and then
I'm going to go Jim update no - or doc
this is going to update all of our gems
just to make sure that we have
everything all exactly the same and then
we can type in Ruby - V and you're going
to see that we have Ruby 2.2 which is
great and rails - V and we have rails
setup as well now what you're going to
want to do is install compass and
compass requires sass so it's going to
automatically install it and your
Jim install compass you might have to
type sudo inside of there you can see
there it goes got it and everything is
all installed now we'll be able to go to
SAS - V and we see that we have SAS
installed and compass - V and we see
that we have compass installed alright
now that we have everything installed
exactly how hard is it going to be for
us to create a project where we're just
going to type in compass create and then
I'm going to call this test one whatever
you want to call yours and there you go
and it's going to automatically generate
Aang for you I'm going to type in well
let's clear this LS and there's test one
we're going to change our directory to
test one and you can see everything here
is installed if I want to open up all
this in sublime I'm just going to type
in su BL and a dot and there it's going
to go and it's going to open up
everything that I need now let's go
through here and actually take a look at
what we got so the first thing we got
here is config dot RB it's very
important let's open it up and go
through exactly what we have here this
basically has all of our configuration
two faults plugins how CSS should be
generated and two what directory here
you can see all of the different
directories we're going to be storing
all our stuff in so we have our CSS
directory or sass directory our images
directory and our Java scripts directory
this HTTP path right here could be
either be a forward slash for you or it
could have two dots preceding it mine
actually has two dots so you can
experiment with that a little bit down
here you can see our output style and we
have a couple different options here
nested is going to use indents when
defining nested styles we already took a
look at nesting compact is going to put
all of your CSS code on a single line
instead of using a different line for
each one of the properties when they're
defined and compressed is what we're
going to use when we're ready to get
live and this is going to remove
comments as well as whitespace
I accidentally skipped this guy up here
where we have our plugins if you're
going to want to use a plug-in you're
just going to type in require and then
whatever your plug-in name is like for
example sussy is a plug-in which I'll
probably cover in the next
toriel if you'd like to see that which
is allowing us to use grid systems
inside of here which is very useful as
well this guy down here if uncommented
is going to allow to use a helper
function to point to your images folder
which we define right here and I'll get
more into that a little bit this guy
down here if active will display
comments that are going to point to the
sass source for your CSS and that is
basically everything you need to know
about the config dot RB file now there's
other ways to come in here and create
projects we could also come in here and
be very very specific and we go compass
create and if you wanted to define your
sass directory like say sass like this
and then you want to give specific names
as basically what it is and this would
be e CSS and then your JavaScript
directory this would only be used if you
didn't want to use the default Java
scripts dir and let's just say we went
in at the BJS
and then to stay here on one line if you
also wanted to define your images
directory you could do it just like that
and that's all you need to type in and
hit enter and compass would go in and
create your projects with your very
specific folder names but for this one
I'm just going to stick with what we
have right here might as well go in here
and this is basically what everything's
going to work here are going to be all
your sass file C F CSS and this is where
you're going to be putting those in and
here is going to be the style sheets
that are going to be automatically
generated for you based off of the code
you write up here so like we saw before
whenever we wanted to generate
cross-browser CSS and we wanted compass
to do that for us well we would define
what we would have up here in very
simple formats and then compass will
generate the complex cross browser code
down here okay so now what I'm going to
do is create a bunch of partial files
that are going to allow us to split up
our CSS and what's really cool about
sass is it's going to allow us to split
it up while at the same times not
require multiple HTTP requests for each
part so we're just going to go into this
guy and then go into sass and we're
going to create a new folder and we're
going to call it partials and there that
is and that's automatically going to
show up in sublime text and here we are
over in sublime text then there's
partials now we're going to create a
whole bunch of different files so new
file and what
gonna call this guy let's file save as
and let's call this guy underscore base
the underscore is very important and
then s CSS and let's save that and let's
just create a whole bunch more so create
new and then file save as we're gonna
have everything here done in the
beginning variables which is where we're
going to store all a bunch of variables
and make sure this is an underscore up
here if you can't say underscore and
then dot s CSS there was base that was
the first one if you didn't see it and
then create another partial save as and
let's call this guy layout this is
normally where you would just just
define the layout part of your
application I may or may not use that in
this tutorial haven't decided yet
and newfound what I mean by layout is
how the elements layout on the screen
and not the properties within them and
save as and this guy is going to be
mix-ins which are really cold you're
gonna see those here in a second
and then one more partial file and file
save as and this guy is going to be
called normalized thought s CSS and save
that and here we are so let's go over
into base first I'm going to cover
something sass comments if you want to
make a single line comment this is how
you make a single line comment and just
know that this may not be rendered after
this is turned from an S CSS file into a
CSS file and then you have multi-line
comments comments and they would end
with a star and a closing bracket and we
normally put them like this and these
guys will definitely show whenever
everything is compiled into a CSS file
however it may not show where you want
if you want to guarantee that it's going
to show and it's going to show exactly
where you place it you will use what are
called loud comments and they come out
exactly like this just put an
exclamation work and there you go and
you can be positive that those will show
up now what I want to do is define the
normalized part of my application and
this is the guy that I'm using I'll put
a link in the description as well
there's all numerous of these guys out
there that you can use you can use
whatever you
prefer if you already have something but
basically if you don't know what this is
just a collection of HTML elements and
attributes that are going to normalize
the styles across all of the browsers
and you can just copy this guy right
here and then jump over here to
normalize s CSS this guy right here and
paste that in and save that and you're
done with normalize s CSS now I want to
go into the variables section and what
I'm going to do here is I'm just going
to copy and paste in a whole bunch of
variables so you can see exactly how
those are defined that I'm going to use
maybe site-wide and then from this point
on I'll be able to just refer to them by
their little dollar sign on whatever
name I provide for them right here and
some people whenever they're naming
their variables like naming based off of
where the color will be used while
others prefer names that represent the
color I basically just go with the flow
and just do whatever but I do prefer to
have variable names that are logical
that sound good to me and/or our good
representation of whatever color I'm
using another thing just to cover pretty
much everything you can also define it a
fault so let's say we have a default
let's call it text color and let's make
this black and then put exclamation mark
and default and what we're saying here
is this is the default that's going to
be used only if a value isn't set or
signed anyplace else so now that we have
all of those set up what are we going to
do to make them show up in our
stylesheet well we're gonna have to come
over and create the Styles part of our
style sheet something to come over here
to the sass area and just go a new file
and I'm gonna save this as file save as
Styles dot SC SS and save that and I
saved it in the sass directory and I
forgot something over here in our
terminal what we want to do is first off
let's make sure we're in the right
directory we are if we want compass to
automatically update or create our CSS
files every time that we change any of
the files in our project in general
we're going to do is type in Compass and
watch and enter and it's going to go in
there and automatically generate all of
the files for us and all of the changes
that we make you can say that it's going
to compile those files and if we jump
over here you can now see
there if we click on styles dot CSS it
is there as well as being up here
alright so now that we have that inside
of there how we going to import compass
for example we're going to say import
and then compass got that installed and
also we're going to want to import our
variables so import and this is in
partials and variables and then we're
going to import more of these but let's
also import partials normalize and now
we have everything that we've created so
far all inside of our Styles dot s CSS
file actually I put them in the wrong
one let's cut this out here I stuck them
in the Styles dot CSS we want to close
that let's just save it and then close
it and then go into this guy and paste
that in there and file save and there
we're ready to go now I'm going to go in
here and create my index.html file so
just go in here and I'm gonna go and
copy and paste in all my index files you
can see everything right there it's just
all this stuff is going to be available
in the description underneath the video
I'm going to save this file save as in
my main project area as index.html and
save that and you can see right here
what I have style sheets and styles dot
CSS save and now you can see if I load
this in the browser here is all of the
HTML it's kind of a mess but over the
course this tutorial to fix a whole
bunch of things I am however going to go
in here and paste in some just regular
CSS code in my Styles dot s CSS file and
I'm going to be adding a whole bunch of
other different things but this is just
basically a regular old CSS and you can
use that of course in s CSS as well
without any problems and let's save that
and reload it and see how things have
changed and there you go you can see
that some things are looking good and
some things are a little bit of a mess
I'm going to jump back over into my
project and I'm going to go a new folder
and this is going to be called images
and remember I didn't automatically
generate these but I showed you how that
you could and I might as well just come
in here and put Java scripts as well
Java scripts and of course we want to
make sure those are the same as our
config file but before we do it's jump
in images and paste in some images that
I have here for my website and there's
the config dot RB file and yes it's
called Java score
ups and images and this is called images
and JavaScript so everything's looking
good okay now that I pasted those images
in let's reload it and it looks a little
bit nicer but we're gonna fix some
things off now I'm going to jump over
into base s CSS and I'm going to define
some defaults that I'm gonna have site
wide that weren't covered by the
normalized part of my site so I'm going
to say something like body and defined
font family as well as Arial Helvetica
and all these other different things
inside of here another thing I want to
do is I want to define the text color
using what's called a mixin so I'm going
to go into my mix in s CSS and mix-ins
are basically just functions that we can
pass values into and they're going to do
certain things for us and how we define
one is we go mix in and we can say
default text color and we'll just call
this TC for text color and then we'll
say color is TC right like that another
thing you could do is if you wanted to
have a default inside of here in case
this function was called and nothing was
passed inside of it we could do that
just like that but for this yeah let's
just leave it that way so this is
basically just going to allow us to
define a color now let's jump back over
into the base CSS file and let's use
that mixin so if we want to define our
color here we're going to say @include
default text color which is the name we
gave for our function and let's pass in
black and what that's gonna do for us is
automatically going to spit this guy out
with whatever color was passed inside of
there exactly right here so it's a nice
easy way for us to define some different
things that we want and you can do a lot
of things with mix-ins as we're gonna
see it here in just a moment also would
kind of want to come in here I want to
put a wrapper it's gonna surround
everything let's come in here and fix
some of these issues that we see here in
our browser in our website and what's
happening here is we're having a lot of
overlapping issues so what we want to do
is we want to make sure that our
rendered box elements include the
padding and the borders and whatever
else and make sure that they fit with
the width that we define inside of our
website and how we can do that is just
go to star and here I'm just going to go
WebKit box-sizing and go border-box like
I said it's just gonna say if we define
a width include the padding and the
borders and such with whatever width we
define inside of it you're gonna see
here in a second what this looks like
and box-sizing border box and then
finally box-sizing border box another
thing I'd like to demonstrate here is
nesting again because it's pretty
important with sass just want to make
sure that you understand it let's say
that I specifically want to target all
of my link tags inside of here this is
inside of an article element all of this
stuff inside of here
so we're going to say article and these
are all inside of P tags just so you
know what I'm talking about here we are
let's go down here and you can see right
here is article and P tags and then the
links inside of those P tags that's what
I want to focus in on here and a let's
say that I want them to have my default
blue color and here I'm using a variable
of course that if I want them to change
to something else on hover
I just put and and hover like that and
let's say also focus let's do that as
well that's how easy that is make sure
you put the colon inside of here and
then whenever they have hover or focus I
want to change the color on those to
what I called Duke blue and then I could
also change my color once again if it is
visited color and let's have this be
blue gray and file save that now what I
want to do is use all of these styles
that I have here over in my Styles SCS
file so I'm going to have to come in and
import those as well and you're going to
see that for example right here how this
doesn't line up and all kinds other
different things are going to be
corrected here in a second say oh that's
terrible let's fix that and we already
did we just need to import the base and
we also need to import the mix in so
let's go partials mix-ins
and then we want to do the same thing
for base so base then we're going to be
doing a ton of things with compass using
css3 styles and to use them you're going
to have to
Porthos will say compass dot css3 if
I'll save and see some things fixing up
look say things started fixing
themselves up see it doesn't get all
wonky now whenever I do this and the
images size well and so forth and so on
that all comes from this guy right here
if you were wondering that's very very
useful if you ever have problems with
your stuff not fitting well there you go
that's a solution so let's jump back
into styles doe-eyed s CSS and this is
we're gonna spend the rest of the
tutorial and I'm basically just going to
walk you through how to change a whole
bunch of different things right here on
the screen okay so the very first thing
I'm going to do is I'm going to be
messing around this navigation it's over
here so where is that guy here it is
it's called vertical navigation sidebar
left you can see right there and what
I'm going to be doing is focusing in on
all of these link tags and I'm going to
change their color and I'm also going to
change their color based off of hover as
well so how do we do that back into
Styles let's just go right down here to
the bottom so if I want to target that
of course just left sidebar and of
course this is left sidebar links this
guy right here and it's defined as a
class and that's good because I want to
target a whole bunch of them so sidebar
links and what do I want to do here well
the a or the links inside of here I want
to go display:block just going to make
them like block elements so then I want
to change them their color to main green
and let's say that I want to change
their opacity their default opacity to
70% however whenever they are hovered
over I want to come in here and go hover
and change their opacity in that
situation to a hundred percent let's
save that and reload this and you can
see now there they up see the opacity is
changing so that's just another
demonstration of nesting inside of here
very important that's the reason why I'm
covering it a whole bunch of times
let's say I also want to put a border
underneath of each of these guys except
for the last one how exactly what I do
that well I would go left sidebar and I
normally break these up into more files
and just keeping it this way so that
pretty much everything's here all in one
place so we can go border bottom and
let's make this two pixels solid and
let's use Maine green again close that
off and if I want to put
order everywhere except with the last
child well I could just go like this
and last child and say border:none for
that one and reload and you could say
everybody has a border underneath of it
except for the last child which is right
there the thing it's neat to know is you
can also nest CSS properties so example
let's say I have just example element
just do this just to do it I could come
in here and save border and then top one
pixel solid blue and then do exactly the
same thing for the other ones and that
will allow you to change those default
properties as well that we're not going
to use that just one to cover it because
it came to mind another thing that's
neat is we can extend existing
properties so let's say down here we
have a riddle it says a dad and his son
riding their bikes and crashed and blah
blah blah blah blah whatever it doesn't
really matter let's say we want to
target the riddle part of that down
there and here is the riddle it's an ID
see there it is right there jump back
over here what we're going to do here is
to find some things and then use it
inside of another element so we say 20
pixels padding and margin top 10 pixels
we can then say riddle answer which is
what follows underneath of it and take
everything or all the properties defined
right here and put them down inside of
here and how we do that is go at extend
and then riddle and that's going to take
all those properties and put them there
just as if they were there all along and
then we could also good margin talk 10
pixels actually for this one I wanted to
make this a little different let's make
this background color and let's make
this Alice blue and reload it and you
can see that there it shows up and at
the background and the padding were
borrowed from Riddle and used in the
riddle answer which is right there we
could also come in and define properties
or create properties just so that we can
extend them and that basically just
means we would go and put a % and dotted
box for example and border and let's say
Duke blue so this is only being created
so that it can be used by other elements
and margin and
pixels and zero pixels now what we can
do is go to riddle answer again
and extend input dotted box inside of
there and it's going to take all this
properties and add them and there you
can see now it has a dotted box around
it so that's also neat get into some
different properties we can play with
let's go with our left sidebar links
play around with those and let's call
border color and let's say if we want to
lighten it we can just go lighten and
we're going to pass in Maine green as
the color we want to use for our border
color and let's say we want to lighten
it by 70% we can do that reload and you
can see that those got lighter tons of
these things packed inside of sass as
well as compass and you can do the
exactly the same things with darken so
just put dark and inside of there
instead of lighten so I'll save reload
and there you can see it's almost black
you could also generate a 180 degree
compliment of a color let's open up a
website here we are this is an example
of what I'm talking about you would be
able to change the hue of the color
inside of here by moving around inside
of this wheel inside here so let's say
we want to go search button which is
this guy right up here there's your
search button and let's say that
whenever it's hovered want to change its
color background color do the complement
of whatever it is so let's have it be
main green is the color that I want to
work with and now you can see when I
hover over it changes to that complement
color I'm going to go through a whole
bunch of these you could also invert a
color so let's just go search button
hover play around with this a little bit
and adjust my hue again it's going to
just the hue of whatever color you pass
inside of here so if I have Maine green
and I want to change it by 90 degrees to
be very specific I can do that it's sort
of like a purple now instead of a
burgundy color now I'm going to come in
here and play around with these guys a
lot or vertical navigation so let's jump
in here and look at exactly how those
are all set up
there's our vertical navigation what I'm
going to be doing is grabbing the
children elements of this vert and Ave
that we have right inside of here and of
course it's an unordered list and I want
to get list items so I'm going to be
targeting the child elements of these
list items
and how we're going to target those is
just go vert now unordered list list
item the list item I want to target and
child and I want to get the first child
background color and let's say I want to
use desaturate just going through each
one of the different types of things you
can do here you can see on the right
side of the screen how it's going to
work and desaturate 80% for the orange
that i pass in and you can see exactly
how that looks now I'm basically just
going to do the same thing using
multiple different color change options
that are available with SAS so let's say
that with the second element inside of
that vertical navigation I want to try
saturated it saturate just change it
like that
and I can just leave it be 80 and orange
and reload it you can see how that
changed somebody that's more of a color
expert than I am might be able to do a
little bit more but I'm just going
through and showing you all the
different things that are available and
you can play with them on your own you
could also define transparencies for
these guys by just going in and typing
in fade out and there's another one I
can't remember it's called like
transparent eyes it's the same thing it
does exactly the same thing as fade out
fade out always made more sense to me so
I use fade out let's say I wanted to use
orange again but I wanted to do 50% and
reload and you can see all that changed
they come in here and zoom in it's going
to get a little bit wonky but since I'm
focusing on on the vertical navigation
that doesn't really matter I could also
make the color more opaque and for this
one I would use fade in and orange that
works and let's just have this be 0.8
whoops change the first child let's
change the fourth child instead we could
also define RGB colors inside of here so
let's change this to a 5 and this is
just going to be a little bit of red a
little bit of green a little bit of blue
and a little bit of alpha red green blue
alpha then we're going to define the
amounts that we want for each one of
these so let's have this be 0 0 205 for
our alpha okay you do really crazy
things like mix two colors together and
then find the percentage of the first
color and how you do that is by typing
in mix
and then we could do something like
yellow is going to be the first color we
want to mix together with a white and
how much yellow do we want this to be
let's have it be 50% and you can see it
change right there now it changes to 6
so we can keep everything on the screen
all at one time
there's tons of coloring options I'm
showing you a lot of them but not all of
them
you could also force a color to be
grayscale so you pass it a color and you
say give me the grayscale version of
this color that I give you so let's just
come in here like that you could see
there we are
I don't know if you'd ever want to use
that but there it is nonetheless and
then one that's really completely crazy
is a just color and it's going to allow
you to change red green blue hue
saturation lightness alpha however
you're only going to be able to adjust
red green and blue or hue saturation and
lightness so you have to decide what's
most important to you and when you're
defining red green and blue you're going
to have to use colors or numbers between
200 and 255 when you're working with Q
you're going to use between 0 to 359
saturation is going to be 0 to 100
lightness is going to be a number
between 0 to 100 and alpha is going to
be 0 to 1 you're going to use
percentages or you know like 0.5 0.8
point whatever and like I said before
you can only use RGB or hue saturation
and lightness and how we're going to use
adjust color much the same here let's
change this to an 8 and then we're gonna
say adjust color - color and then we're
going to pass in let's have this be mean
green again and then let's define how
much red we want so I will do this it's
like that and then how much green do we
want let's say it's 40 and then how much
flu we want so when you use that base
color and then adjust it based off of
that and there is our weird greenish
color and its greenish because there's
more green than there is anything else
and there's no red and da-da-da-da-da
change that to 9 and we can only do red
green or blue or hue saturation and
lightness so this time let's do hue
saturation and lightness
thing else is the same as still a just
color and this is going to be main green
again or at least that's what I'm going
to use main green if you want to adjust
your hue we're going to put 30 inside of
there and or saturation just so you can
see what those look like let's make this
40 just have this be simple lightness
let's have that be 30 and then alpha
let's have it be 0.2 and there's that
crazy blue there's a bunch of different
things you can do here
you could also shade colors like I said
I'm covering pretty much every color
type of thing you can play with here
let's throw another one in there and
let's change this to 10 still have a
couple more children to play with you
could say that you want a shade of
whatever color you put inside here I'm
going to use yellow and again all these
different guys are coming from my
variables that I defined early on so
let's go in here and say I want a shade
of yellow and I need to tell it what
percent of black I want combined with
this let's say 50% and reload you see
it's very sickly looking yellow and
likewise there's also a tint which is
going to allow you to define how much
white you want to add the adding into it
so let's just go tint let it be let's
change this to yellow again just you can
see the difference between them so let's
say yellow and how much white let's say
50% up make sure you spell it
tint and not 10th and now you can see
it's a little bit prettier
alright so that's basically all the
different color things you have
available for you inside of sass now
let's go in here and take a look at some
other built-in mix-ins that come with
compass so let's go down here - well
let's shrink this down a little bit all
right so let's come down here and round
the corners on this guy down here like I
said whenever you use the mix-ins that
come with compass it's going to
automatically generate all the
cross-browser stuff for you so let's
change the riddle answer and I want to
use the compass version so that it will
automatically generate all the good
stuff so a border radius and here you're
going to use I'm going to use 5 pixels
make sure you put it inside of this
brackets like that and let's say I also
want to add a box shadow for this and
here we just go include box shadow
and I'm going to define my horizontal
offset make that five pixels my vertical
offset five pixels how much I want it to
blur let's say five pixels my spread two
pixels and what color do I want it to be
I want it to be gray and making sure
that's semi colons there and reload it
and there you can say now the corner
edges are rounded and it also has box
shadow and also you're gonna see the CSS
that was automatically generated so it's
going to style sheets and styles and you
can see how all the commenting works and
all that stuff and let's scroll way down
here to the bottom and you're gonna see
that it automatically went in and
generated all the cross browser stuff
for us that's that's why it's really
cool it's just oh it's very very cool
now let's go in here and take a look at
how we can add a text shadow to this guy
right up here well that guy is called
main title so I'm going to go main title
like this open that up and again I want
to use a built-in mix in that comes with
compass text shadow and let's say that I
want to use an or a gba color here and
let's just put blue inside of here and
my percentage and then how much of an
offset that I want horizontally how much
of an offset will I want it to
vertically and how much blur do I want
wait like this and reload it and you can
see there's a shadow there or at least I
hope you can see that play around with
these things are really cool it just
opens up a whole plethora of different
things you can do we could also create a
gradient so let's say I wanted to turn
this boring bar into a gradient up here
and in my css3 tutorial I have a whole
bunch of gradient type stuff and let's
also say that I want to create this just
so that I can use it here and down here
how exactly do I create a set of
properties just to use them somewhere
else % that's it and let's say that I
want to call this main green gradients
and then I want to include put
background image and I'm going to say
that I want a linear gradient and I need
to define where it's going to come from
well I can either put left right top or
bottom or left top right
bottom left bottom right depending upon
where I want that to come in from I'm
just gonna keep it simple have it be
left and I'm gonna say that the start
color that I want to use is my main
green and I want it to take up 80% of
the screen and then I want white to take
up the rest of the screen okay so I have
that defined I want to use it inside of
other things so let's say I want to use
it in my footer just go footer and then
go at extend means that I want to use
this other style that's already been
defined for me and gradient and you can
see way down here the gradient that
shows up inside of there I made a little
bit of an error I put a comma right
there
don't do that leave that out all right
so that's how we style that and I could
do exactly the same thing for the
horizontal nav bar that I have at the
top of the screen just by going in here
and changing footer to horizontal nav
and this guy here is going to change
into a gradient now and you can see that
it did and it went and created a whole
bunch of other things in our regular old
CSS files which is really cool as well
now these guys over here are bothering
me so let's say I want to target one of
those and change the image inside of
there I'm also at the same time going to
show you how SAS makes it very easy to
grab images from your images folder no
matter where they are so you won't have
to use real long names so I want to
target an image and I want to target an
image with this specific alt of
programming frameworks there you go and
if I want to change the content I'm
going to change the image that's inside
of there I go
content image and image - URL and then
whatever the name of it is inside of my
images folder so image dot Peng is what
it is semi colon and right like that it
loaded it directly inside of there so
really neat it's very useful to have
everything set up like that like I said
over here you might have dot dot forward
slash you might have just a forward
slash it's going to depend you're going
to have to try it and then fix it and do
it
make it work well it wouldn't make sense
for this I could also have this
automatically get the size of whatever
this is so if I say width and I want to
get my image width I can do so and I
could also get my image height just by
pasting those inner see this kept me
from having to do that but either way
what this is going to do is it's going
to tell me what the image width and
height is of the actual image and then
store it there it's going to make it
grow really big and look ugly but
whatever I just want to show you that
it's very useful not in this context
it's not useful but very often in other
contexts it is useful so I wanted to
cover that another thing we can do is
some of the neater things where we can
scale and move different elements on the
screen horizontally and vertically using
compass so it's going to be like cross
browser or type of stuff that's going to
be automatically generated so let's say
that I wanted to take this little logo
that I have up here and I want to scale
it up and I want to move it to the right
side of the screen how hard is that to
do well I just go little go target my
logo and then @include scale and let's
say I wanted to increase it twice its
size horizontally and vertically there
you go that's all it took to do that and
also I can come in and let's do a
transform and let's move it in the
x-direction 700 pixels you would go
transform translate X 700 pixels right
like that and then let's say that I want
to translate y 10 pixels there we go and
to do another one let's say that we also
want to scale it I could put the scale
inside of here that would work as well
and let's say that I also want to rotate
it on negative 45 degrees that's how
hard that would be to do put the
semicolon there so you put everything
all there on one line and just do
whatever you need to do and you can see
it's over here and it's off the page and
it's but it is rotated and it's
everything so just pulling this stuff
out of my head here for the large part
and get a little bit of goofy things but
either way you get the gist of what's
going on there it is on the screen it's
on its side and it's rotated and all
this other different things okay so what
else can we do well we could use compass
to put a drop shadow on all of our text
inside of let's say this paragraph tag
here which in this situation is going to
be this second child element inside of
there so once again we got article and I
want a paragraph tag and I want the
ninth or I want to get the second child
element and if I want to put some text
shadowing I could go filter drop shadow
and let's say I want to put a gray one
and let's do an offset horizontally one
pixel one pixel vertically and there we
go make sure this is child not Chao
reload it and there you can see is a
little bit of a drop shadow inside of
there let's go make this a little bit
stronger and there we are change the
blur amount to two pixels and there you
can see the blur that's on there there's
a filter effect we can also use with
compass another thing that's neat is we
can change different properties based
off of conditions so let's define this
is just a regular variable I'm going to
call it riddle color and this is how we
define those and how we use conditions
if let's just use an if statement here
so let's say if the value of Riddle
color is equal to blue which it's not
what we want to do is we want to define
riddle as having a background color of
Alice blue and then we could come in
here and say else make sure we put a
tells else like we use in other
programming languages let's go and
change the background color for Riddle
again and this time let's just make it
ash gray and reload it and you can see
that these guys change to ash gray down
here so that's how we can use if and
else statements to change things based
off of pretty much any type of condition
but there's a condition where the value
of this variable is gray and if we would
change this to below let's just do it
we are reload it and now it's below okay
so it works either way the thing we can
do is there's an option to use for loops
inside of SAS
let's go PRC 2% yellow and what we're
going to do is we're going to color
these guys down here in this navigation
ever increasing values of yellow so our
starting off percentage of yellow is
going to be 5% you can use percent you
can use numbers you can use anything how
we use a for loop is going at 4i from
and then let's define what we want so we
have 414 of these guys so we're going to
say 1 through 14 that's how long our for
loop is going to execute and then if we
want to change the color of this we just
go vert nav which surrounds all those
items in our left sidebar navigation
talking about this guy right here
and ul and Li and we're going to be
targeting list items
so we'll say 9th child and then if we
want to put a number inside of here we
have put a number sign like that and
these brackets and then I so it's going
to sort through and it's going to cycle
through each one of those it's one of
the coolest things ok and then if we
want to change the background color for
each one of those it's going to cycle
through each of them and let's say we
want to mix yellow and we want to mix
white and then the amount of yellow we
want to put inside of here is going to
be % yellow like that our variable we
defined and then outside of this after
we exit the fewer loop we can go percent
yellow and that's going to be equal to
percent yellow plus 5 percent and you
could say I would ever increasing values
of yellow say started off at 5 percent
went all the way up to a hundred percent
I like that what else can we do one
other thing that's really cool is we can
use spriting with compass and basically
what it's going to do is it's going to
combine a whole bunch of images that we
provide in a folder and it's going to
convert them into one image which is
going to limit our server quests so to
do that inside of our images folder you
can see here I have icons and here's all
these icons what it's going to do is
it's going to take all these and it's
going to create them all in one image
and it's going to automatically going to
provide the proper background image
definition and location for each of the
elements in the sprite so let's say
sounds like a lot of work let's go in
and show you how easy it is so
first off we need to import the ability
to work with sprite so we'll go import
and this should be at the top of the
screen but I just want to keep
everything here at one place so
utilities and sprites like this then if
we want to import all those images we go
import and we define whatever the folder
name was which it was icons and then we
go a star thought they're all ping files
and this only works for ping files as
far as I know and then we're going to
say include all icons sprites like this
and now what we'll be able to do is
target I have you don't see them here on
the screen but if we go in here wait at
the bottom the screen you can see right
here see I have a class called icons and
a whole bunch of these divs inside of
here with the specific class names so I
can come back over here and I can just
go icons target that and then clock app
and then to include it I just go include
icons sprite and clock and then do this
for all the other icons then I could go
icons and everything inside of that div
and define the height I'm just doing
this so everything shows up on the
screen you can use these wherever you
want 64 pixels and reload it and there
you can see all this sprites show up
inside of there and what's also cool is
we can open this up and styles - all
this stuff is being generated and you
can see all the background positions for
all of our different items is going to
be automatically generated for us so see
icons there's a clock there's the diary
and the background position for each of
those so they're all in one image
automatically it creates them and you
can see all of that stuff right there so
really cool and then the final thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to mess around
this ugly table that's down here see
there's this table I'm going to show you
how to clean that up make it look a
little bit nicer with compass and we're
going to say import and compass
utilities again and tables is where this
guy resides and the name of this is
baseball stats and we're going to
specifically target our table and we use
something called scaffolding table let's
include table scaffolding and we
to find our inner border by going
include this is something else you guys
can play with different colors and
things and there's our border and
borders and let's just make this four
pixels and let's define the table color
as table color it's a variable I think I
saved over here I guess I didn't so
let's go and put this right here
table color and let's just make it black
just to keep it simple so there's table
color semicolon there so that's going to
define the inner table borders and we
can also define our outer table borders
outer and let's just keep this simply
let's make this Duke blue there we are
and then we can handle table striping as
well include alternating rows and column
and let's say that I want my even row
color to be Alice blue and my odd row
color to be ash gray the intersection of
those let's just make this table color
and then let's say that I want my header
color to be white
save that reload it and there you can
say Alice blue and gray and all the
table headers are always so here you go
guys there are a ton of different things
you can do with sass as well as compass
hope you guys enjoyed this tutorial
please leave your questions and comments
below otherwise till next time