In this tutorial,
we'll learn how to automate a Chrome browser
using WebDriverJS.
To get started, open up Terminal.
I'll assume you have
Node.js and chromedriver installed,
which are the prerequisites for this tutorial.
However, if they're not installed and you're on Mac OS X,
you can install the prerequisites via Homebrew.
Check out the links in the description
for more information.
Now let's create a folder for our project and
install the node module `selenium-webdriver`.
Let's install our node module by typing in
`npm install selenium-webdriver`
Great, it's installed.
We know our module
has been installed by typing `ls`
to list and we see a new node modules directory.
And if we `ls` inside node_modules,
we'll see we have our 'selenium-webdriver'.
Now let's start coding via the node command line.
To do that, we type in `node` and press Enter.
In here, you'll see we have our own node REPL—read, evaluate, print, loop.
And we can do a lot of node commands here.
First, let's require the installed
node module `selenium-webdriver`.
We' ll do that by typing in
`var webdriver = require('selenium-webdriver'')`
And you'll see that it returned `undefined`,
but it means that it has required it successfully.
Let's build our Chrome browser.
To do that, all we do is we type
`var driver = new webdriver.Builder().forBrowser('chrome').build()`
And if we typed that correctly,
you'll see our ChromeDriver has popped up.
Excellent.
And now I'm just going to
resize it just to make it look all good.
Great.
So now we have our Chrome browser open.
Let's do something interesting.
Let's go to 'google.com'.
To do that, all we do is type driver
and use the `get` method
and there we put in the url `http://www.google.com`
And we'll see that it takes us to Google.
Let's make a search result.
We'll want to get the element for that search box
and we can do that by hitting inspect
element
and then once inspect element opens up,
let me just hit it again,
you can see that
this input has a class, has an id, and has a name.
So we have a lot of choices
in how we can get the search box.
Let's use the name.
And we see that the name is 'q'.
Here we can select the element by typing in
`driver.findElement(webdriver.By.name('q'))`
and you'll know that it selected it because you'll
see that is now focused on the input.
Then take the above method
and then add a `sendKeys` method.
And here we can send in, for example,
"hello world"
And once we hit Enter, you'll see that
it has searched "hello world"
If we want to click the button, how would we do it?
That's pretty simple.
All we do is go to the element,
hit inspect element again,
that there's a class for this button
and we can now click on that button.
And to click it, we do the same thing
`driver.findElement`
and this time we can do
`webdriver.By.className`
and then put in the class name.
And then here we add the `click` method.
Hit Enter and you see that
it clicked and refreshed the page.
Now there is another way to select the element.
Here when you saw that we did `driver.findElement`
You can see it's a bit verbose having to type `webdriver.By`,
`name` or `id`
or `className` or `tagName`
or whatnot.
There's another way we can do this.
We can also do `driver.findElement`
and in here put inside a hash object.
And in this hash object
we can put in what we want to find,
which could be `name`,
which could be `id`,
which could be `tagName`,
which could be `className`.
And then we make sure that the value
is equal to that.
So that if we do this and then we hit `sendKeys`.
And then let's say we want to put in "webdriverjs" as our query.
Let's see what happens.
You see,
now it appended "webdriverjs"
to our "hello world" query we made from before.
So what else can we do?
Well we can click the button
but we can also hit the Enter key
once the input is selected
and it's currently selected.
So let's do that.
We type `driver.findElement`
and then it's the same input as before,
so it's the name of "q"
and then here,
we can then send keys
and use `webdriver.Key.ENTER`.
And once we hit Enter, we see that
it refreshes the page again.
Now let's click the first search result.
To find it as we usually do,
you right click it, hit 'Inspect Element'.
This time, let's get it by the `xpath`.
So then here to select it,
we do `driver.findElement`
and then put in `xpath` as our key
and let's paste in the `xpath` string.
Then, we type `click`.
Cool.
Now it's taken us to a GitHub page.
Can we also get the title of this page?
To do that it's pretty simple.
All we do is `driver.getTitle`.
Now in this `getTitle` method,
you probably assume that you pass in the title
somewhere inside this anonymous function.
Right?
Well actually,
since WebDriverJS uses a kind of control flow for promises,
we use the `then` method
and then in the `then` method
the title can be passed inside.
We don't have to name this title,
we can name this `foo`
we can name this `bar`
but `title` is pretty semantic so let's keep it as title.
And here, we can simply just `console.log`,
it's JavaScript's way of printing inside the console,
the title.
Let's hit Enter,
and we'll see
that the title is
this thing,
which is the same as in the browser.
And finally let's quit our driver.
To do that,
all we have to do
is type `driver.quit()`
and that'll close our driver.
Now, we've typed a lot of commands and
you'll probably want to write a script
in which you can call that script
and that script will do everything automatically.
Right? You don't want to always open up node
and then type all these commands line-by-line.
It's nice if you want to experiment,
play around, and learn what commands does what
and how to do which thing.
But we're lazy, right?
We want to automate things.
So in node,
we can actually save
the history of commands that we typed.
In here, we can see that there's a `save` method
that's given in the REPL session.
And it says we can save all evaluated commands
in this REPL session to a file.
So let's do that.
We type `. save`
and then let's call it `session.js`.
Cool, now our session is saved.
Let's exit the node REPL by hitting
`Ctrl-C` twice.
Let's hit `ls`
to see we now have a `session.js` file.
If we just `cat` it,
we'll see that it's all our commands.
Let's go inside the file
and clean it up a bit.
You can use your text editor of choice
whether that's Sublime Text,
any text editor,
or Vim.
My preference is Vim so I'm going to use it.
So now that I'm inside Vim,
let's clean up a bit.
You can see you on the first line,
we require `selenium-webdriver`.
We're keeping that.
In the second line, we're building up the chrome driver browser.
Keeping that as well.
Third line, we're opening up 'google.com'.
Fourth line we're now finding the element,
the input element,
in which we're sending in our search query.
Well, we have two of the same commands,
one is just finding the element,
the second is setting the keys.
So let's keep the second one.
And here, we can keep the keys 'hello world'.
And then here we click it.
Well let's use the `enter` command instead.
So let's look for where we hit the enter button
and we'll keep that.
And here we click the first search result.
And then after that we got the title,
logged it out,
and then quit the driver.
Let's run it and see if it works.
And you see that it failed.
Well, why did it fail?
Let's look up and it says,
`NoSuchElementError`
Now why is that it doesn't find the element?
Well remember,
in WebDriverJS, it's asynchronous
which means it doesn't block.
So in that regard,
your script could have ran,
but the browser could have not loaded the element yet.
Here we'll need to tell the script to kind of poll the browser
for you know, maybe a few milliseconds or maybe even a couple seconds,
just to see that everything has rendered and the element is found.
Imagine you're on a website and
that things are loaded asynchronously using JavaScript.
You know when if an AJAX GET is being made,
you can't expect that the element is immediately present.
So here we'll need to use a `wait` command
and we can do that by going back into our script.
Here let's add the `wait` command by typing in
`driver.wait`
and then here we use `webdriver.until.elementLocated`.
And here we can copy in the xpath.
Great.
And then, the next line should then work
because it has found the element,
it has waited until the element has been located.
Technically, you could also add in
a second argument here and this will be
the timeout.
You know it could be like a thousand milliseconds
or however much time you want to
have it polled before it times out.
Alright let's save it and run our script again.
Great, it has run successfully.
And this ends our quick tutorial on how to use WebDriverJS.
Thanks for watching.