in this video we're going to cover an
introduction to webdriver IO webdriver
IO is a framework that provides bindings
into selenium so that we can write
automated functional tests there are two
ways to run webdriver IO one is through
a normal node script there's also a
command-line interface which we'll get
to in a later video today we're going to
be testing a landing page that we have
for a visual regression testing email
course free online course that you can
sign up for if you're interested and we
just want to do a little a quick little
test to see that our form works
correctly here it says email can't be
added because this is not a correct
email address but this is what we want
to test that when we enter the email
into the form it takes us to this page
I'll open up the command line I'm going
to make a new directory called test
files I'll go into that directory and
then the first thing I'll do is
initialize a new NPM repo so that we can
save our package dependencies now that
we have our NPM module set up the next
thing we'll do is install webdriver IO
I'm going to save it as a dependency a
dev dependency so that if we want to
install this same folder on another
computer it will get automatically
installed I'm also going to install
another package called selenium
standalone and this will provide us a
way to run a selenium server locally I'm
going to install it globally so that we
can run it from the command line there
are other options for not installing it
globally that we can run through
webdriver i/o and we'll get into that in
a later video I'm going to go ahead and
install selenium standalone so it
downloads the selenium webdriver that
the selenium servers that we need and
the chrome driver that we need as well
and then I will start selenium
standalone so we have a selenium server
up and running so that webdriver IO can
use it the next step we'll go back to
our command line we're going to create a
new directory called tests and then
we're going to edit a file called my
first test and then I'll go ahead and
open that up in simple
texts now that I have my file open I'll
refer back to the webdriver i/o
documentation and I'm just going to copy
these three lines and explain what's
going on there so the first thing we do
is we require the webdriver i/o module
that's provided when we ran the
webdriver i/o installation the second
thing we'll do is pass set up some
options for our webdriver i/o selenium
instance this is saying we want to start
Chrome and we're going to get a client
by telling webdriver i/o we want to
start a new remote session with options
in it if we refer back to the
documentation you see the client needs
to initialize itself here it's going to
go to a URL which is different from the
one we want to go to it's going to set a
value in the search it's going to click
a button then it's going to get the
title we're going to basically copy
these steps the only thing we're going
to do is change our URL and the ID of
the element we want a different input
and then also the idea of the button
that we're going to test so I'm actually
just going to copy this over and then
come in here and change my URL and then
for my value I'm going to go in does I
want the value of this input box so I'll
go ahead and inspect that element and
you can see it has an ID of MCE
email if you're familiar with MailChimp
that's a MailChimp email input and then
instead of webdriver IO I'm going to say
test at test comm so there's two ways I
can submit this form I can click the
button that says submit my first lesson
today
she has an ID there another option is to
get the ID of the form itself and
instead of clicking the button I'll hit
send a submit form action and I'll pass
in the ID this is just a generic CSS
selector this could be a class if you
wanted it to be a class it could just be
an HTML element whatever you want it to
be we're going to stick with IDs because
they're very useful because the IDS
don't change that often we don't have to
wait for the page to reload here
webdriver IO is smart enough to figure
that out for you it isn't going to
output that title though so we'll see
what this title is okay so now I have my
test the next thing I do is I go back
into my terminal and I've run my test so
you can see
my title is learn visual regression
testing with webdriver IO both pages
have the same title so one other option
we can do because we can't really tell
that this has gone to the new page so
we're going to go back into our test and
instead of get title we're going to just
do a URL these commands can be found in
the API documentation search for URL and
what we want is get URL and then I'll
change this to URL and we'll say the URL
is URL okay we're going to go ahead and
run this again and now you see here is
my updated URL with some information in
it so you can see it as actually changed
and that's my test
you